You are listening to Golden Rule Radio,
your weekly discussion of the precious
metals markets and the markets closely
associated with the metals. I'm Miles
and I'm alongside nobody this week. Both
Rob and Tory are out this week. Miss you
guys and look forward to having you back
in the studio next week. Each week, we
like to take a few minutes to look at
the technical analysis of the metals
charts and cover the underlying
fundamentals and news that helps move
and predict the markets. So, today we're
taking a look at some pretty aggressive
moves in the precious metals and the
equities markets.
So, moving into the weekly charts, we're
going to start off with gold, which is
actually pretty flat this week.
Technically down about a quarter of a
percent. Not too much to really write
home about, but gold is sitting just
under 4,700 at 4,685. And that's
actually going to stop there because as
we move over
to silver, holy smokes, silver up 13% on
the week. Looks like it's screaming back
up to $90 an ounce. It's currently
$87.70
and possibly not showing an inkling of
stopping here in the next at least
couple of days. So, we definitely want
to take a longer look deeper into the
silver chart here in a moment. So,
silver beating everybody, not flat like
gold, up 13%.
Platinum, little bit behind silver.
Platinum is up 9% last week and another
5% this week. So, platinum up about 14%
over the last 2 weeks, which is what
silver's done just in the last week.
Platinum, now again, firmly above 2,000,
currently sitting at $2,150.
And sister metal to platinum, palladium,
go in the other direction down 2 and
1/2% since last week. So, the platinum
to palladium price ratio is starting to
spread out again. Palladium currently
sitting just above 1,500 at 1,507,
1,507.
The stock market, we're going to look at
a couple different markets here in a
minute, but starting with the S&P, just
to give us a broad indicator, the S&P is
up almost another 1% here uh this past
week. And continues on the tear that
it's been on, currently sitting at
7,445,
and nothing but green candles for the
S&P as it continues to rise here over
the last couple of weeks. And the dollar
index, this is the DXY index, up about
half a percent. Currently sitting at
98.5.
So, pretty much across the board flat to
up except for palladium, which we like
to look at from an industrial standpoint
as a counterpart to platinum. So, since
I get to decide where we go, and I'm
actually going to start us off with the
US dollar this week because I think
there is a
good parallel I want to draw here. You
know, a lot of us have gotten very
accustomed to taking a look at the DXY
through the years,
but recently here, and Tori and I have
had this conversation privately over the
last couple of weeks, recently here,
it's becoming less of a broad enough
indicator to really look at. So, if you
really look at the DXY chart here,
you're seeing what appears to be a
pretty long-term rising trend in the US
dollar with a corrective period coming
back. Now, the problem with the DXY is
the DXY index is about 50% weighted
against the euro.
So, when you overlay the DXY against
another indicator like the Fed's
trade-weighted indicator that brings 25
or 30 additional countries in and is a
much broader look at the strength of the
US dollar compared to other trade
currencies around the world. You kind of
see a changing pattern there
internationally.
And where I tend to find this
interesting and why I think this matters
into the conversation here is I think
you're starting to see a segregation
between the US dollar and euro
denominated assets compared to other
trade nations out there that we work
with where you're starting to see a
weakening of the US dollar over time
which probably also means a weakening of
the European markets over time as well
when you look at it compared to the DXY.
So, there's a pretty good chance that
going forward with the show, we're going
to be taking a look at both of these
because we do have to recognize that a
lot of the geopolitical conversation
that people have been having here
recently is not about the United States
and Europe. It's about China. It's about
South America. It's about other Asian
countries within the Asian block and
certainly the Middle East as well. So, I
think it's fair to say that we need to
look at the US dollar from a broader
standpoint here to recognize that the
inflationary concerns we're having here
domestically are presenting themselves
internationally
when you look at some of the other trade
weighted countries. Now, between us and
Europe, it does look like we're pretty
much in lockstep or continuing a trend
that we expect. But, when you bring
those other countries in, it does start
to look a little bit more negative. So,
I think that's kind of a good place to
start with as we're looking at some of
these other pricing because when we're
looking into the charts on a number of
the other metals and then other markets,
we are weighing those metals against
what's happening in the US dollar.
You can also go out and say look at gold
versus the Japanese yen or the Chinese
yuan or the Mexican peso or anything
else, but here we're looking at it
against the US dollar and the dollar
index comparisons, which is primarily
what you'd consider kind of a US or
European-centric market. And frankly,
that model is starting to shift when you
look at some of these other
trade-weighted currency pairs. So, let's
definitely take a little jump over to
gold. Gold tends to be the reason why
our company exists and the currency that
we all like to get back to. So, the
thing here I wanted to discuss and I
highly highly highly this week recommend
going and checking out our other show if
you're not already listening to it
weekly. This week David and Kevin over
at the Macleavy Weekly Commentary had a
long conversation both about things that
we tend to avoid here because everybody
else is talking about them like what's
going on in Iran and the Strait of
Hormuz and how that's affecting oil
pricing and the drawdown on oil reserves
internationally right now due to the
conflict in that area. Dave and Kevin
give us a really strong deep dive into
that. And there was a piece in there
when I was listening to Dave talk
earlier that I think very much applies
to what we're seeing in the metals
market right now and that's a shift in
policy thinking. Kevin brought up a
point this week where as somebody who
likes to look at charts, what I'm
looking here is trend and momentum
typically caused by the buying and
selling habits of investors. So, when I
pull the price of gold up, when I can
overlay things like moving averages and
Fibonacci retracements and look for
trend lines, what we're getting into
here is seeing some patterns back and
forth of where you tend to see the fist
fights between bulls and bears play out.
And sometimes those things are very very
clear and sometimes frankly the market
just goes a direction and throws the
baby out with the bathwater. We've seen
those periods back in January and
February, but now we've gotten back into
some more traditional trading. So, when
I listen to David and Kevin talk, Kevin
brought up a great point here this past
week where for the last 40-50 years from
a charting perspective, that's how we've
looked at the precious metals market,
specifically the gold market. As it has
primarily been controlled by traders.
We've talked about this for a number of
weeks now. The amount of gold held
within various treasuries around the
world, I think reserve assets got as low
as 9 or 10% at one point internationally
where 60 years ago it was closer to
100%. Well, here over the last 10-15
years we've seen that start to
transition where all of a sudden the
40-50 years that we've been looking at
how the precious metals trade, you've
been applying the same type of thought
process to precious metals that you
would to other markets like equities or
bond markets where you're trying to
predict a investor class
and the way they vote with their wallet
towards different types of assets. So,
now we're seeing a policy change and the
policy change has been pretty clear that
gold is not the 4,000-5,000
year-old pet rock, but gold is becoming
the replacement currency for the US
dollar. That may be interim,
but I'm thinking back through my 20-some
year career here where I've listened to
a number of clients present concerns as
to if we're looking at a failing dollar,
what replaces the dollar? Is it going to
be the Chinese yuan? Could it be the
euro? 20 years ago everybody thought the
euro was going to become the world's
great next financial superpower. More
recently, it's been expectations about
the Chinese yuan. But for some reason,
we seem to have all forgotten that the
little yellow metal that could,
throughout all of human history, has
been the replacement currency that
people go back to. And I think that's
what we're certainly starting to see
again now as those international
reserves are starting to build back up
to 20, 25, 28% of total and starting to
outstrip the US dollar on an
international scale for the number one
position for reserve currency holdings.
So, I think we are seeing the currency
transition that everybody has been
fearful of, and that's certainly getting
reflected in the price. When we go over
and we take a look at the gold price
here recently, we've seen a fair bit of
stability in the gold price following
the big run-up. So, if you look at this
run-up in the gold price going back to
earlier this year, pushing us well over
that $5,000 mark, culminating this
spring into January, beginning of
February, you're really looking at a
gold run that didn't just start last
fall. You know, we're looking at a major
gold run that really started back at the
middle to end of 2022, down around
$1,600 gold, with a continuation climb
all the way up to 5,600, let's say, give
or take. A relatively shallow correction
back down. Now, we talked about this
last week, where we've had this kind of
two-steps down pattern in the price of
gold, and it seems to be holding that
pattern relatively reasonably. This is
the conversation about traders
maintaining control now.
Now, when you look at the last couple of
months, that wasn't traders maintaining
control. You know, that's when you throw
the baby out with the bathwater, as I
just said. But now we're looking at
relatively stable trading here in the
very short term. So, now the question
becomes, okay, where do we go from here?
And this was something we've started to
hint at and I want to take a minute just
to draw a couple lines on the charts
here because we're looking for a couple
of things to play out here as traders
maintain control within this market on
both the upside and the downside and the
bulls and the bears are trying to figure
out who's going to gain the momentum
edge and sort of push things the other
direction. We're still looking at gold
maintaining a declining pattern with two
lower lows and probably two lower highs.
Now, recently we've had a little bit of
a push up in gold and as we look at the
silver chart here in a second, I may
change my tune a bit, but until we break
out of this particular pattern, you
would expect to see gold continue to
stair-step down to some previous support
levels which would have been put in back
around the previous bottom around 4,000
or we could even go back to the previous
market top that we finally broke up
above back in August and this would have
been around 3,400. So, the assumption as
markets stay mentally sound, let's say,
is that you're going to have a period of
explosive either growth in this case or
sometimes decline,
then you're going to have a correction
back down, a reversion to the mean, and
then you're going to wait for traders on
one side of that argument to take
control or not. So, we're looking at
some pretty consistent and healthy
trading back and forth in gold. The
bigger concerns that other more
geopolitical positions are going to take
a look at like say our McElvenny Weekly
Commentary which tends to look at things
with a much broader brush than we do,
they're looking at these massive
sweeping policies on a government or
major corporate level that take months
and years to filter their way into the
person-to-person pricing of things. When
we're looking at it in the short term,
that's just the day-to-day movement of
trader action. We are seeing that trader
action start to pick up right now.
They're watching the CME Groups both of
volume and open interest positions,
which have been relatively stable in
gold, but starting to slightly increase
here over the last week or so. Gold to
me remains in the trading range we're
looking at. I'm looking for potentially
some lower entry prices here, and
certainly hoping for that. So, now we'll
move over to silver because it gives us
a slightly different story, and I think
this is the key point to take a look at
through the markets this week. Now,
silver on the other hand followed the
same kind of pattern where we had a
couple lower lows, but silver's trading
range has been staggeringly large. We've
mentioned this over the last couple of
weeks, silver's trading range has been
huge, anywhere from around on the top
end $95,
and on the low end maybe $60.
That's a 50-plus percent trading range
from bottom to top in the short term.
That's extremely volatile and very hard
to try to plan for. Now, the fun thing
with silver, which can also be the
dangerous thing, is the silver bugs out
there have been throwing some numbers
out that I don't disagree with, but I'm
concerned about timing. Like, do I think
silver's going to go to three or four or
500 bucks an ounce? Yeah, at the current
inflation rates and in the way we're
going, of course it will. Do I think
it's going to happen this summer? Well,
that I'm not willing to place a bet on,
but I still don't want to eliminate that
as a concept from the way I'm looking at
these charts going forward. So, let's
take a look at this here from the silver
position. As we've been stepping down
here, something I said last week is
looking at this massive trading range,
I felt that what we were probably doing
is climbing our way back up to the top
end of a declining trading range. And
we're getting very, very close to that
now. You know, with us at $87.50
an ounce, that's probably going to put
us up another couple bucks to around $90
an ounce. So, we're going to bump our
head on the first ceiling here for the
silver market. So, we've currently
returned about 50% of the decline. So,
if you look at us topping out at around
120, coming all the way back down to 60,
pushing back up to 90, that's halfway
between the two. That'd be about a 50%
retracement back to the upside. And
that's really where we're going to see
silver hit its head pretty hard here at
around $90 silver. Now, if we happen to
push above that, if we do happen to push
above that, I think there's another
trading channel that probably by the
time we get there is going to take us up
to a double top. So, what's crazy to me
here is we could see silver,
which back at the end of March,
beginning of April had declined all the
way down to 60,
we could see silver return to 120,
and then turn around and come back down
from there, putting a double top in.
Now, I'm not saying I think that's going
to happen. You could also see silver
break above that and continue that climb
upwards, which it will do eventually.
But, we really are in a position here
where you're looking for momentum on one
side or the other, and are the bulls or
the bears going to claim ownership of
this market going forward, especially
specifically the silver market. So, what
I love about seeing this type of
reaction in silver is this takes us over
to a third chart I want to look at here,
and that is the relative price of gold
versus silver, what we call the gold
silver ratio, and talk about relatively
often here. The
which had been for the last number of
years running at relatively high levels
in that how many ounces of silver does
it take to buy 1 oz of gold?
What is the price of gold in terms of
ounces of silver?
And we've seen a repeating back and
forth, I would argue rising, but we've
seen a repeating pattern in that over
the last 20-30 years, where there will
be periods of time that gold
dramatically outperform silver, and then
there'll be periods of time where silver
dramatically outperform gold.
We have thus far seen silver
dramatically outperform gold in a very
short period of time.
And we're pushing down to a rising trend
line channel, in fact, in a rising trend
line channel, as you can see on the
charts here, to the downside. Now, there
are lower numbers we could end up
getting to here on the gold-to-silver
ratio. And that's the thing I definitely
want clients to pay attention to right
now. Is this is the time where you start
looking at your precious metals
position. You start looking at the
balance you have between the various
metals, and you can potentially look for
opportunities to swap your gold into
silver, your silver into gold, and pick
up sometimes significantly more ounces
than if you had bought the other in the
first place. So,
with us pushing into this channel,
there's certainly an opportunity that we
could see it get a little bit better, go
a little bit lower, which is why I think
when you start getting into this range,
you want to start taking measured steps
out. So, I would encourage anybody out
there who's sitting on significant
percentages of silver at these price
ratios. If you're 50% silver, 60, 70,
80% silver, consider touching base with
your advisor here at McAlvany Precious
Metals. We can check your math for you
real quick. We can look at where you
came in to your silver position
initially. Maybe you were in the 70, 80,
90, 100 to 1 ratios back through
post-COVID kind of 2021 to 3
and look at starting to transition some
of that silver over into gold sort of in
measured steps as we hopefully see the
gold silver ratio continue to decline
from here.
So, it gives you something to do while
you're watching these markets, which in
their short-term trading cycles
sometimes make no sense.
It's constantly getting questions like
"Hey, silver's going up right now. Why
is gold holding still?" Or "Hey, gold's
going up right now. Why is silver going
down?" And we'll get questions like that
sometimes and sometimes you just have to
take a step back and say, "Okay, the
day-to-day markets don't have to make
logical sense on a day-to-day basis.
They just have to follow patterns and
make sense when you start to stretch
those timelines out a little bit." So,
there are things you can be doing in the
precious metals market right now that
may not necessarily include buying more
or selling some because of the dollar
profit. Now, long-term, you really want
to hold those positions if you can cuz
inflation's going to take care of the
dollar price on a long enough timeline.
But, there are things you can be doing
within the metals themselves to be
increasing that position. And by turning
10 oz into 15, 15 into 20, it really
becomes irrelevant what the dollar price
is. I mean, honestly, 10 years from now,
if I've doubled the amount of gold I
have, I don't really care what the
dollar price inevitably ends up going
to. I don't care if silver's 300 or 500
or
200 or 10,000. It doesn't matter. If I
can turn 500 oz into 1,000, that's a
multiplicative effect over the course of
time anyway.
So, it's a different approach to looking
at an investment portfolio. A lot of our
clients are already involved in this
conversation. Encourage you to continue
having it with your advisor.
Before we run out of time here, I want
to touch on a couple things on the back
end. Platinum, we're looking at
increases in platinum and silver. So,
from an industrial metal standpoint, we
are looking at increases.
Where we're not seeing them on the gold
side as much over this past week.
I think that's because of what we
discussed earlier and David brought up
in the McAlvany Weekly Commentary, gold
has become a policy discussion, whereas
silver and other industrial or precious
metals within the industrial framework
are going to be more of a traded
discussion. So, starting to see that
disconnect pretty aggressively here
between gold and silver, I think is
because we're starting to see gold
transition from a precious metal to a
currency conversation.
Whereas things like silver are staying
within the realm of investable assets
and are being treated as an undervalued
asset, which silver still is, even at
almost $90 an ounce, still significantly
undervalued compared to its relative
pricing 30, 40 years ago. Uh platinum is
the same and I still think platinum is
probably the best deal in the precious
metals right now at its pricing. So,
uh quick glance over at the equities
markets cuz I thought this was pretty
interesting this week. There's
definitely starting to see a separation
of haves and have nots in relation to
the equities market. The equities
markets has been doing exceptional. No
one denies it. But, so is our cost of
living. And I think we're starting to
see a segregation between people who are
concerned about the cost of living rise,
but seeing an offsetting return
on their 401 Ks and stock portfolios.
That's one group of people.
Another group of people is just
concerned about the cost of living rise.
And I think that the increase valuation
of your stock portfolio keeping up with
the increased expense of your grocery
store bill
for most Americans, one doesn't cover
the other. So, we're definitely seeing a
segregation there where the equities
markets is starting to rise and we're
hearing coming out of Washington despite
the events taking place in the Strait of
Hormuz, boy, the stock market's still
doing great. It's well the stock market
doesn't really benefit as many people at
on a day-to-day basis as we would like
it to. The cost of living and oil price
increases definitely having a more
significant detrimental effect than the
equities market is having a positive
effect. But, we're starting to see a
segregation between the different market
sectors that are certainly propping up
different aspects of the market. You
know, we've talked about this for a
number of years how we have a small
collection of primarily tech stock
companies propping up the entire market
as a whole responsible for the majority
of the growth. So, just for fun, I sat
down and charted out all 30 of the S&P
stocks and there is a very clear winner
when you look over the last four or five
years with Nvidia leading the charge as
expected up a little over 3,000%
whereas most of the other 29 companies
are up, you know, 100, 200, 300%
but the bulk of the weight is getting
carried by a very small handful of
companies and that's much more
representative within a broader market
that's covering multiple different
market sectors like the S&P compared to
a much narrower look at your top of the
New York Stock Exchange food chain.
Propped up almost exclusively by Nvidia.
So, that's going to do it this week for
Golden Rule Radio. As always, we
appreciate you stopping by. If you liked
what you heard, we encourage you to head
on over to our website at macalvany.com.
That's m c a l v a n y dot com. You can
also find us on Twitter at ICA Gold and
Facebook at Macalvany Financial. And as
always, if you'd like to discuss your
personal portfolio with one of us here
at Macalvany Precious Metals, you can
reach us at 1-800-525-9556.
Thanks for listening. Have a great week.
>> [music]